You may have heard
the expression
“knowledge is power.”
Well, today we’re going
to give you more power
to control your
diet and lifestyle
by giving you the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we continue
our series
on how industries impact
dietary and health guidelines.
And pick things up
by taking a close look
at corporate criticism of
scientific nutrition literature.
While randomized controlled trials
are highly reliable in assessing
interventions like drugs,
they’re harder to do with diet.
Dietary diseases can
take decades to develop.
It’s not like you can
give people placebo food,
and it’s hard to get people
to stick to assigned diets,
especially for the years it
would take to observe effects
on hard endpoints like
heart disease or cancer.
That’s why we have to use
observational studies
of large numbers of people
and their diets over time
to see which foods appear to
be linked to which diseases.
And interestingly, if you
compare data obtained from
observational population studies
versus randomized trials,
on average, there is little evidence
for signiﬁcant differences
between the findings.
Not just in the same
direction of effect,
but of the same general
magnitude of the effect
in about 90 percent of the
treatments they looked at.
But wait, what about the hormone
replacement therapy disparity
I talked about in the last video?
It turns out when you go
back and look at the data,
it was just a difference
in timing in terms of
when the Premarin was started,
and they actually showed the
same results after all.
But even if observational trials
did provide lower quality evidence,
maybe we don’t need the
same level of certainty
when we’re telling someone to eat
more broccoli or drink less soda,
compared to whether or not you want
to prescribe someone some drug.
After all, prescription drugs
are the third leading cause of
death in the United States.
It goes heart disease,
cancer, then doctors.
100,000 Americans
are wiped out every year
from the side-effects of
prescription drugs taken as directed.
So, given the massive risks,
you better have rock-solid evidence
that there are benefits
that outweigh the risks.
You are playing with fire; so,
darn right I want randomized
double-blind, placebo-
controlled trials for drugs.
But when you’re just telling
people to cut down on doughnuts,
you don’t need the
same level of proof.
In the end, the industry-funded
sugar paper concluding
that the dietary guidelines
telling people to cut down
aren’t trustworthy, because
they’re based on such
“low-quality evidence” is an
example of the inappropriate use
of the drug trial paradigm
in nutrition research.
You say yeah, but what were
the authors supposed to do?
If GRADE is the way
you judge guidelines,
then you can’t blame them.
But no, there are other tools,
like for example, NutriGrade,
a scoring system specifically
designed to assess and judge
the level of evidence
in nutrition research.
One of the things I like
about NutriGrade is that
it specifically takes
funding bias into account,
so industry-funded
trials are downgraded.
No wonder the industry-
funded authors
chose the inappropriate
drug method instead.
HEALM is another one,
Hierarchies of Evidence Applied
to Lifestyle Medicine,
specifically designed
because existing tools
such as GRADE are
not viable options
when it comes to questions
that you can’t fully address
through randomized controlled trials.
In a way each research method
has its unique contribution.
In a lab, you can explore the
exact mechanisms, RCTs can prove
cause and effect, and huge
population studies can study
hundreds of thousands of
people at a time for decades.
Take the trans fat story, for example.
We had randomized controlled
trials showing trans fat
increased risk factors
for heart disease,
and we had population studies
showing that the more trans fats
people ate the more
heart disease they had.
So, taken together, these
studies forged a strong case
for the harmful effects of trans
fat consumption on heart disease,
and as a consequence,
it was largely removed
from the US food supply,
preventing as many
as 200,000 heart
attacks every year.
Now, it’s true that we never had
randomized controlled trials
looking at hard endpoints,
like heart attacks and death,
because that would take years
of randomizing people to eat
like cannisters of Crisco every day.
You can’t let the perfect
be the enemy of the good
when there are tens of
thousands of lives at stake.
Public health ofﬁcials have to work
with the best available
balance of evidence there is.
It’s like when we set
tolerable upper limits
for lead exposure or PCBs.
It’s not like we randomized
kids to drink different levels
of lead and saw who grew up
to have tolerable brain damage.
You can’t run those
kinds of experiments;
so, you have to just pull
in evidence from as many
sources as possible and
make your best approximation.
“Even if RCTs (randomized control trials)
are unavailable or impossible to conduct,
there is plenty of evidence
from observational studies
on the nutritional
causes of many cancers,
such as on red meat increasing
the risk of colorectal cancer.“
So, if dietary guidelines
aiming at cancer prevention
were to be assessed with the
drug-designed GRADE approach,
they’d reach the same conclusion
that the sugar paper did—
low quality evidence.
And so, no surprise a meat-
industry-funded institution
hired the same dude who
helped conceive and design
the sugar-industry funded study.
And boom, lead author saying we
can ignore the dietary guidelines
to reduce red and processed
meat consumption,
because they used GRADE methods
to rate the certainty of evidence,
and though current dietary
guidelines recommend
limiting meat consumption,
their results predictably demonstrated
that the evidence was
of low quality.
Before I dive deep
into the meat papers,
one last irony about
the sugar paper
the authors used the inconsistency
of the exact recommendations
across sugar guidelines over
a 20-year period to raise concerns
about the quality of the guidelines.
Now obviously, we would
expect guidelines to evolve,
but the most recent guidelines
show remarkable consistency,
with one exception: the 2002
Institute of Medicine guideline
that said a quarter of your
diet could be straight sugar
without running into deficiencies.
But that outlier was partly
funded by the Coke, Pepsi,
cookie, candy-funded institute
that is now saying see,
since recommendations
are all over the place
(thanks in part to us),
they can’t be trusted.
In our next story, the
meat industry comes up
with a perversion of
evidence-based medicine.
A series of articles published in
the Annals of Internal Medicine
culminated in a recommendation
suggesting people
keep eating their red
and processed meat.
Nutrition researchers
savaged these articles.
The chair of the Nutrition
at Harvard called it
“a very irresponsible public
health recommendation,”
and the past Harvard Nutrition
chair was even less restrained.
“It’s the most egregious abuse of
data I’ve ever seen,” said Walter Willett
“There are just layers
and layers of problems.”
Let us start to pick
through these layers.
First of several serious
weaknesses was that the analyses
and recommendations were largely
based the so-called GRADE criteria
which I talked about
in my last video.
The authors erred in
applying the GRADE tool,
since that was
designed for drug trials.
GRADE automatically scores
observational studies
as “low- or very-low” scores
for “certainty of evidence,”
which is exactly what you want
when you’re evaluating
evidence from drug trials.
You want a randomized double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
to prove the drug’s risks and benefits.
However, the infeasibility for
conducting randomized clinical trials
on most dietary, lifestyle,
and environmental exposures
makes the criteria inappropriate in
these areas, since it would involve
controlling people’s daily diet
and following them for decades.
“You can’t do a double‑blinded
placebo‑controlled trial
of red meat and other foods
on heart attacks or cancer.
“For dietary and lifestyle
factors, it’s impossible to use
the same standards for drug trials.”
Imagine telling one group
of people to smoke
a pack of cigarettes every
day for the next 20 years
to prove that cigarettes
cause lung cancer.
And how could you
make it double-blind,
have the control group
smoke placebo cigarettes?
Yet, in the meat papers,
they were downgrading studies
due to lack of blinding.
Well duh! In nutrition trials
how are you going to blind people
to the fact of what they’re eating?
GRADE is just the wrong
tool for diet studies.
In fact, the authors
admit that the reason
their recommendations
differ from all the others
is that other guidelines have
not used the GRADE approach.
And the reason is “you can’t
randomize people to smoke,
avoid physical exercise, breath
polluted air, or eat a lot of sugar
or red meat and then follow them
for 40 years to see if they die.
Now, that doesn’t mean
you have no evidence.
It just means you look at the
evidence in a more sophisticated way.”
And alternative approaches to
GRADE exist, like, for example,
NutriGrade, which have specifically
been developed to evaluate
evidence from studies on
nutritional and lifestyle factors
So, are the author’s appeals
to standards of evidence
motivated by a genuine interest
in getting to the bottom of it
or just to advance the
ﬁnancial interests of industry,
as the same lead author
had done previously
at the behest of soda
and candy companies?
“The tool he employed in his meat
and sugar studies could be misused
to discredit all sorts of well‑
established public health warnings,
like the link between secondhand
smoke and heart disease,
air pollution and health
problems, physical inactivity,
and chronic disease, or trans fat.”
Industries could use it to sow
doubt in any field where randomized
controlled trials are not
feasible, such as climate change.
What are you going to
have, some placebo planet?
Strict adherence to GRADE
guidelines could even be used
to question the link between
smoking and lung cancer.
I know you can’t
randomize people to smoke,
but can’t you randomize
people to quit?
Here’s a randomized
controlled trial of the effect
on aged men of advice
to stop smoking.
Of those randomized to quit,
13.7 percent died
within the study window,
whereas of those in the control group
who got no special instruction,
only 12.9 percent died.
In other words, it didn’t work.
Disappointingly, the researchers
concluded, we find no evidence
at all of any reduction
in total mortality.
Wait, so is smoking not
bad for you after all?
Of course not. Anyone
see the fatal flaw?
They didn’t randomize
people to quit.
They randomized people
to advice to quit smoking.
It’s not like they could lock
people in a room for a few years.
At the last follow-up,
the stop smoking group
was smoking 8 cigarettes a day
compared to 12 cigarettes a
day in the control group;
so, it’s no surprise there
was no difference in mortality
since there was hardly
any difference in smoking.
And the same thing with diet.
There have been massive
randomized dietary trials:
the Women's Health Initiative,
the Multiple Risk Factor
Intervention Trial,
that wasted hundreds of
millions of dollars,
because people just flat out failed
to follow the dietary advice.
So, the groups ended up eating
similar diets at the end
so had similar
disease outcomes,
just like the randomized
smoking-quit trial.
It’s not like the failure was a result
of inexperienced investigators;
these trials were conducted by some
of the very best research teams
who invested enormous efforts
to achieve their goals.
But it just shows you can’t really
run decade-long randomized trials
that require changes
in eating behavior.
People just won’t do it.
Randomized controlled trials
couldn’t even show an effect
on mortality of smoking,
which is pretty remarkable,
considering that smoking is
one of the most powerful
known risk factors in the world.
So basically, the foregone
conclusion putting any kind of junk
to the test in this manner would
echo the new meat report conclusion
that people should “eat whatever
they want and do whatever they want.”
It’s like a hijacking
of evidence-based medicine.
Of course, we want the
best evidence possible,
but the whole process is
now being “manipulated and misused
to support subverted
or perverted agendas.”
“It’s very exciting and
attention-grabbing to say
there’s no need to
reduce meat intake.
It’s less exciting to say we reviewed
studies to evaluate the validity
using a system not meant to
evaluate the validity of these studies,
and what we found is nothing.”
When asked whether
physicians can advise persons
whether a salad is healthier
than a bowl full of sugar,
one of the senior co-authors
of the meat papers responded
that physicians should
tell persons that
“the quality of evidence is low;
so, it depends almost entirely
on their preferences.”
“When GRADE criteria do not
allow us to strongly recommend
against smoking a cigarette
with your bowl of sugar,
we believe that alternative
grading systems are preferable.”
Did you know that the same
person paid by Big Sugar
to downplay the risks of
sugar was paid by Big Meat
to downplay the risks of meat?
Here’s the story.
A series of articles published in
the Annals of Internal Medicine
recommending people
just keep eating their meat
was decried by nutrition researchers
as irresponsible and unethical,
a travesty of science,
an assault on public health,
and the most egregious abuse of
evidence that they had ever seen.
There were calls for retraction
even before it was published
from eminent public health leaders,
from a former US surgeon general,
a former president of the
American College of Cardiology,
and the directors of preventive
medicine and nutrition institutes
from Harvard, Yale,
Tufts, and Stanford.
In my last video I explained
the how, the method by which
they manipulated the science,
but never really got to the why.
I mean, the lead author's
similar attempt
to discredit the sugar guidelines
was explicitly paid for by an
industry front group funded
by the likes of Coca-Cola, Dr. Pepper,
Mars candy bars, and Pepsi.
But if you look at the meat
paper at the panelists' declared
conflicts of interest, they all
say they didn't have any,
including the lead author
who was involved
in the sugar study,
whose primary funder wasn't just
representing Big Soda and candy,
but the likes of McDonald's
and one of the largest
meat packers in the world.
Yet Johnston didn't disclose that
as a potential conflict of interest
when he switched from exonerating
sugar to exonerating meat.
What did he have to say for himself?
Even though the sugar
study was published in 2016,
he got the money for it in 2015,
outside of the three-year
mandatory disclosure window.
This is the same guy who said
the industry front group had no role
in writing their paper until
the Associated Press revealed
the truth, and the journal
had to publish a correction.
But Johnston doubled down this
time, saying "it is tenuous at best
to suggest that his earlier work
on sugar had any influence
on how his team made the
new meat recommendations."
The important thing is, "We have no
relationship with the meat industry."
Oh really? A few months
later the truth came out.
Correction in the so-called NutriRECS
panel meat recommendations.
Oops, Bradley Johnston failed
to indicate he had gotten a grant
from Texas A&M AgriLife,
which gets millions of dollars
a year from the meat industry to
do things like run Beef Boot Camp,
or espouse the health
benefits of beef brisket,
or promote the celebration
of National Bacon Day.
After all, Texas A&M AgriLife
serves pork producers
to improve pork producer profitability.
This is the group that not only gave
Dr. "no-relationship-with-
the-meat-industry" Johnston
a direct grant for over $75,000,
but they officially joined the whole
NutriRECS consortium to provide,
as Dr. Johnston explained,
generous support to impact
nutrition-related decision-making and
policy in North America and beyond.
Yet none of this was
disclosed in the paper.
No even potential
conflicts of interest,
yet they had formed
a partnership with an arm
of Texas A&M partially
funded by the beef industry
to the tunes of millions a year
from the beef industry alone.
Oops. In fact, Patrick Stover,
Mr. "no-conflicts-of-interest"
is the director of AgriLife.
And a month before the
meat paper was published,
Bradley Johnston was
offered and accepted
a tenured position
at Texas A&M AgriLife,
was already working for them
when it was published,
but didn't think to mention it.
So when the Annals
initially sent out
a press release,
which they later corrected,
saying no need
to reduce red or processed meat
consumption for good health,
they may have been simply
acting as a mouthpiece
for meat-industry propaganda.
The pseudoscience presented
in the Annals meat papers appears
to have been written solely
to create doubt and confusion
in the wider population.
The misleading recommendations
were not intended
to convince scientists,
who clearly understand
the nature of the relationship
between meat and health,
and for that matter,
sugar and health.
The pseudoscience is presented
solely to create doubt and confusion
in the wider population.
Frankly, industry will do
what it needs to do to push
as much of its product
into the world as it can, and so
will do what it needs to do
to obfuscate the relationship
between its products
and human and planetary health;
they've done it with
tobacco, fossil fuels,
Monsanto's Roundup,
sugar, and now meat.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.